NYSUT Vice-President's Office, Maria Neira Files. 6174/016
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Committee of Practitioners (COP) No Child Left Behind (NCLB) Pre-Meeting November 28-29, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  Agenda; list of members; Recommendations on the Reauthorization of the No Child Left Behind Act; No Child Left Behind: A Road Map for Implementation, from U.S. Secretary of Education Margaret Spellings, November 10, 2005; presentation points to NYS Committee of Practitioners re No Child Left Behind Act of 2001; fact sheets; AFT document, NCLB: Let's Get It Right; memo to NCLB Committee of Practitioners from State Education Department NCLB Coordinator Raymond Kespel re theme of retreat, reauthorization of NCLB, November 18; memo from deputy education commissioner James Kadamus re proposed amendment to Commissioner's Regulations re uniform violent and disruptive incident reporting system, October 14; handwritten notes. See also No Child Left Behind; see also AFT No Child Left Behind
- Committee of Practitioners (COP) No Child Left Behind (NCLB) November 28-29, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  Materials as above; memos
- Committee of Practitioners (COP) No Child Left Behind (NCLB) 9/14/05, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  Agenda for pre-meeting, September 14; agenda for NCLB Committee of Practitioners, September 14; presentation sheets, Update on Accountability, September 2005; spreadsheet re committee key recommendations and status; flexibility for determining AYP for students with disabilities; Board of Regents press releases, "Five Schools Named as Persistently Dangerous under NCLB," and "511 Schools Statewide 'In Need of Improvement' under NCLB," September 9; memo to school superintendents from State Education Department re testing program for grades 3-8, July 2005
- Committee of Practitioners (COP) No Child Left Behind (NCLB) 5/10/05, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  Agenda for pre-meeting; brochure, New York Public Schools at a Glance: Achievement, Enrollment, Funding, by New York State School Boards Association, 2005; draft document by State Education Department, Supplemental Educational Services, school year 2003-2004; lists of approved providers; School and Accountability Rules Implementing No Child Left Behind, April 2005; presentation sheets, Update on Accountability, May 2005; draft amendment to Commissioner's Regulations re accountability; agenda for forum on the Destination Diploma, May 23-24, 2005; draft document, Supplemental Educational Services (SES) Reference & Procedures, May 2005; framework for New York's NCLB Accountability Plan
- Committee of Practitioners (COP) No Child Left Behind (NCLB) 3/2/05, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  Pre-meeting suggested discussion questions re testing for grades 3-8; memo to NYSUT Board of Directors from vice president Maria Neira re summary of major issues, re revised math standards and assessments for grades 3-8, middle-level education, December 7, 2004; letter (draft?) to Regents from Neira re accountability and test administration and scoring, December 2, 2004; presentation sheets, "10 Years of Standards in New York State: A Data Based Assessment of Progress Made and How Far We Need to Go," March 2, 2005; memo to school superintendents from State Education Department deputy commissioner James Kadamus re Uniform Violent and Disruptive Incident System, January 2005; related materials
- Committee of Practitioners (COP) No Child Left Behind (NCLB) 10/19/04, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  Memo to committee from State Education Department deputy commissioner James Kadamus re next meeting, with attached agenda; State Education Department Learning Standards for English Language Arts, Mathematics (revisited); correspondence from committee member Bill Roney re need for more group discussion time, request to put items on agenda, including consideration of expanding committee membership
- Community College Conference 11/5/04, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Ann Cook see Policy Issues Meeting
- Disney Teacher Awards, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Announcement of award recipients for Disney Teacher Awards
- Johanna Duncan-Poitier at State Education Department 6/21/05, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Agenda, with recommendations for appointments; confidential NYSUT Personnel Committee Principles re promotion when there is a substantial change in the nature of employee's duties, June 16, 2005; letter to NYSUT vice president Maria Neira from Duncan-Poitier as Senior Deputy Commissioner of Education P-16, June 4, 2007
- Johanna Duncan-Poitier 11/16/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Proposed agenda for meeting with Johanna Duncan-Poitier; letter from NYSUT vice president Antonia Cortese to Johanna Duncan-Poitier, deputy commissioner, State Education Department, urging consideration of appointments from segments of the higher education community not represented on the Professional Standards and Practices Board, specifically direct instructional faculty members from SUNY and CUNY, June 19, 2003; letter from Cortese to Duncan-Poitier, urging the appointment of three teachers recommended by NYSUT, July 16, 2004; draft of letter to Duncan-Poitier from NYSUT vice president Maria Neira, urging appointment of teachers to two remaining vacancies on the board, October 22, 2004; State Professional Standards and Practices Board Membership Matrix, 9/04; list of mentoring concerns; NYSUT's Review/Comments re SED Draft Rubric for Assessing District Teacher Mentoring Programs 11/5/04; letter to Richard Mills, Commissioner of Education, from co-chairs of Professional Standards and Practices Board, urging no reduction in 50% rule for full-time faculty in teacher education programs, November 4, 2004; letter to chancellor of the Board of Regents from the Commission on Independent Colleges and Universities re teacher accreditation process, October 20, 2004; letter to deputy assistant commissioner of education Duncan-Poitier from NYSUT vice president Cortese, expressing NYSUT opposition to change in Commissioner's Regulations requiring that a majority of teacher education courses be taught by full-time faculty, September 2, 2004; Report on the Regents Higher Education and Professional Practices Committee Statewide Plan for Higher Education 2004-2012; Certification Concerns under the New Requirements. See also Commissioner Mills
- Johanna Duncan-Poitier and Joe Frey 10/22/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Talking Points for the Meeting with Johanna Duncan-Poitier: Issues Raised by Professional Standards and Practices Board Opposing the Amendments to Section 52/Full-time Faculty Requirements; Teacher Education Program: Need for Full-Time Faculty, with handwritten notation, "Bill Scheverman's comments"
- Early Childhood Education Committee 10/29/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Agenda of meeting of Early Childhood Subject Area Committee; letter to Education Commissioner Richard Mills from NYSUT vice president Maria Neira re draft Regents Policy Statement on Early Education for Student Achievement in a Global Community, with specific comments on policy recommendations, September 29, 2005; memo from State Education Department re policy statement, July 7, 2005; websites of interest
- Early Childhood Education Briefing Papers 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Center for Early Care and Education briefing paper, "Early Care and Education for All: Making a Commitment to Our Youngest New Yorkers," Rensselaerville Institute, November 28-30, 2001; Early Childhood Research and Practice, vol.2, no. 2, Readiness for School: A Survey of State Policies and Definitions, fall 2000; newsletter of Labor Project for Working Families, Labor News for Working Families, noting paid paternity leave time in other countries, summer 2001
- (ED) Election District Meetings ED 1-4 Western / Southwestern NY 11/8/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Remarks by First Vice President Maria Neira ED 1-4 At- Large Directors Meeting, Williamsville, with handwritten edits, re testing issues for grades 3-8, early childhood proposals, unification with NEA, November 8, 2005; Neira biographical sketch; handwritten notes; facilitative memos
- Election District Meetings ED 9-10 Plattsburg 03/11/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Flyer for "Farewell to President Hobart" event; facilitative memos
- Election District Meetings ED 13 Mid-Hudson 09/15/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  Agenda; vice president Neira's remarks to ED 13 meeting in Kingston, re No Child Left Behind, unification with NEA; draft talking points; handwritten notes; alert memo to PreK-12 local presidents re use of Superintendents' Conference Days for state grade 3-8 assessment rating, September 15
- Election District Meetings ED 5-6 Rochester 03/9/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  Agenda for NYSUT ED 5-6 Local Leaders' Summit; draft remarks for NYSUT 2nd Vice President Maria Neira, ED 5-6, with handwritten edits; text of Neira's introduction of Education Commissioner Richard Mills; notes to Neira re attendance by Rochester Association of Paraprofessionals member who would be recognized as School-Related Professional of the Year; candidate statements by Theresa McSweeney and Kathleen Donahue, running for second vice president; answers from State Education Department to questions submitted by NYSUT re grade 3-8 testing program, February 7, 2005
- Election District Meetings ED 15-16 Westchester 1/13/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Facilitative memos
- ED 14 Newsletters Tracey Campaign 9/27/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Flyer to Election District 14 local presidents calling for help in electing Dennis Tracey to the NYS Assembly, noting consistent vote by incumbent to block override of Gov. Pataki line-item vetoes
- ED 13 and 14 Meeting Honoring Hobart/Ianuzzi Culinary Institute 3/17/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  Invitation to St. Patrick's Day at the Culinary Institute for contiguous meeting of ED 14 and 14
- Election District Meetings ED 13 Mid-Hudson (Carol Slotkin) 12/2/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  Agenda; draft remarks for 2nd vice president Maria Neira; facilitative memos. See also Carol Slotkin Conference Call
- Election District Meetings ED 11-12 Oneonta (Dona Vermilya) 11/5/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  Final and draft versions of Maria Neira's remarks
- Election District Meetings ED 11-12 Overheads 11/5/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  Presentation points re No Child Left Behind
- Election District Meetings ED 5-6 Rochester 10/7/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  Agenda for NYSUT Directors' Meeting and Local Leaders' Summit; related memo
- Election District Meetings ED 1-4 Buffalo 10/6/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  Agenda; newsletter, Southwestern Regional Office Report, September 2004; NYSUT Western Regional Calendar; October 2004 WNYPAC telephone bank volunteer schedule; memo re ING Opportunity Plus 403(b) tax-deferred annuity, termination of relationship with L&M Financial Services, September 28, 2004
- Election District Meetings ED 5-6 Rochester 3/11/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  Final Title I Regulations: Alternate Assessments for Students with Significant Cognitive Disabilities: Talking Points; overview of No Child Left Behind; State Education Department paper, Strategy for Implementing the Regents Policy Statement on Middle-Level Education, February 6, 2004; handwritten notes
- Election District Meetings ED 1-3 Amherst 2/10/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  NYSUT Information Bulletins re state assessments in English Language Arts and mathematics for grades 3-8, State Education Department approval of alternatives to Regents exams, district-based teacher mentoring programs, No Child Left Behind requirements for paraprofessionals, High Objective Uniform State Standard of Evaluation (HOUSSE); New York State definition of a "highly qualified" teacher; January 2004 Math A Regents Exam talking points for Executive Committee meeting, February 12, 2004; overview of No Child Left Behind; questions and answers re AFT endorsement of John Kerry; flyers supporting John Kerry, opposing Medicare drug benefit
- Election District Meetings Meeting on Speeches 10/12/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  Memo re meeting on how remarks are prepared for speaking engagements
- Education and Learning Trust 12/13/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  Agenda for Board of Directors meeting; minutes of June 22 and September 27, 2005, meetings; memo from Ro (Rosemarie) Rosen to Maria Neira and Chuck Santelli re interim financial and enrollment report, November 2; memo from Ro Rosen to Neira and Santelli requesting approval for online, in-service courses through Video Journal, October 17
- Education and Learning Trust Effective Teaching Program New Course, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  Proposal to Chuck Santelli from Ro Rosen for new course under Effective Teaching Program, June 16, 2005; course outline and syllabus, "A Framework for Teacher Leadership". See also Effective Teaching Program
- Education and Learning Trust Ro Rosen Meeting (In-Service Course) 10/31/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  Memo from Ro Rosen to Neira and Santelli requesting approval for online, in-service courses through Video Journal, October 17; memo from Ro Rosen re Teachscape; memo from Ro Rosen re database search results for contract language for "lead teacher," guidance for proposed course, October 14, 2005
- Education and Learning Trust Ro Rosen Meeting 9/30/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  Brainstorming agenda; memo from Ro Rosen, with Education and Learning Trust timeline of key events, brainstorm framework, Effective Teaching Program enrollment timeline, 1978-2005; background data for staff brainstorming session
- Education and Learning Trust Ro Rosen: Professional Development 8/25/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  List of areas for discussion, including Teacher as Leader course, need for Education & Learning Trust to have more contact with local leaders
- Education and Learning Trust Ro Rosen Meeting 11/16/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  Memo to Chuck Santelli from Ro Rosen re budget; 2004 new member teacher survey summary
- Education and Learning Trust Ro Rosen Meeting April 13 and 19, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  Memos re Record Schedule meeting, meeting re materials for Learning Trust
- Education and Learning Trust Sungard Powercampus Software Demo 01/23/06, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  Message requesting a meeting with Maria Neira and Chuck Santelli for software demonstration
- Educational Conference Board 12/6/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  Agenda for first annual policy conference, re investment and accountability for student success; conference program; list of attendees; letter to NYSUT vice president Maria Neira, confirming registration; handwritten notes
- Educational Conference Board 11/10/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Educational Conference Board 10/6/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  Agenda; financial statement, October 5 and September 3, 2004; minutes of September 7 meeting; list of dues invoiced to member entities; proposed amendments to Articles of Agreement; list of recurring and priority issues for 2004-05; Preliminary Report of the Charter Schools Work Group, presented October 6, 2004; materials from New York State Council of School Superintendents: 2004-05 Enacted Budget Summary, Assessing the Assessments 2004; county-by-county impact of alternative state aid scenarios for 2005-06
- Effective Teaching Program 12/15/04, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  Updated ELT (Education and Learning Trust) staff meeting agenda for December 15, 2004; memos re December 15 staff meeting of Effective Teaching Program, noting Ro Rosen was director; list of questions, Marketing Phone Conference Follow-Up, December 2, 2004. See also Education and Learning Trust
- Election see Kerry; see also Post-Election Summary
- Ellis Island Medal of Honor 5/14/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  Program of 2005 award recipients; schedule of events; table seating list; flyer congratulating NYSUT vice president Maria Neira on receiving the Medal of Honor; letters from National Ethnic Coalition of Organizations Foundation, Inc., to Neira, informing her of her nomination, January 26 and February 11, 2005; partial list of past recipients; related memos
- English Language Arts, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  Memo to members of NYSUT Subject Area Committees for Elementary Education and English Language Arts re request by State Education Department for review of revised English Language Arts Resource Guide with Core Curriculum, March 11, 2005; list of focus questions; analysis of current ELA core curriculum, comparison with revised core, March 10, 2005; draft of core curriculum, March 2005
- English Language Learners Committee, 2005-2008 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  List of committee members; invitation to first meeting, with tentative agenda, November 29, 2005; U.S. Department of Education No Child Left Behind Biennial Evaluation Report to Congress on the Implementation of the State Formula Grant Program 2002-2004; English Language Acquisition, Language Enhancement, and Academic Achievement (ESEA, Title II, Part A), March 15, 2005
- English Language Learners (ELL), 2003-2005 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  Memo to vice president Maria Neira and Chuck Santelli re proposed legislation, recommending drafting a memo in opposition, March 17, 2005; text of proposed legislation to allow local high school diploma to be given to students who pass a proficiency exam in their native language; NYSUT Special Education Committee 2003-2005 End of Term Report, revised February 2, 2005; report by National Hispanic Caucus of State Legislators, "Closing the Achievement Gap: Improving Educational Outcomes for Hispanic Children," July 2003; Testimony of Aminda Gentile, UFT Vice President and director, UFT Teachers Center to the City Council Education Committee Hearing on English Language Learners Programs in the New York City Public Schools, October 5, 2004
- English Language Learners Bilingual News Clips, 2004-2005 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  Article from New York Times re NYC Mayor Bloomberg's change in position on bilingual education, June 25, 2003; National Task Force on Early Childhood Education for Hispanics web pages re task force mission, list of members, 2004; article from Education Week re persistently high dropout rate among Hispanics, November 17, 2004
- English Language Learners New York State Association for Bilingual Education (NYSABE) Conference March 3-6, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  Newsletter re NYSABE 28th annual conference, recent activities, fall 2004; conference flyers; related information
- English as a Second Language NYSESLAT 3/03/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  Invitation from the State Education Department to Standard Setting Conference for the New York State English as a Second Language Achievement Test (NYSESLAT)
- Executive Committee 9/20/07 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  Report of the executive director; 2007 end of legislative session update (NYSUT legislative program priorities and bills that passed both houses of the legislature); memo re final 403(b) regulations; resolution authorizing location of 2009 Representative Assembly to be moved from Rochester to Buffalo if the labor dispute with the Crowne Plaza-Rochester is not resolved; memo re Citizen Action campaign for comprehensive health care reform
- Executive Committee 12/9/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  Agenda and minutes; agenda of NYSUT Board of Directors meeting; minutes of NYSUT Board of Directors meeting of September 17; procedure for reviewing expiring resolutions; president's report; by-laws of Unity Caucus; agenda for Unity Caucus meeting of December 9, 2005; document from State Education Department, "A Call to Action: Follow-Up to the New York Education Summit"; NYSUT Executive Committee managerial appointments; resolutions referred to the Board of Directors by the 2005 Representative Assembly; 2006 Representative Assembly action items for Executive Committee and Board approval; NYSUT Building Corporation Board of Directors meeting agenda and minutes of December 9; Building Corporation membership meeting agenda, December 10; minutes of Building Corporation membership meeting of September 17, with balance sheet; minutes of NYSUT Executive Committee meeting of November 3, 2005
- Executive Committee 11/3/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  Booklet honoring former AFT president Sandra Feldman; list of potential speakers for Sandra Feldman memorial; outline of oral report of first vice president Maria Neira; letter from Citizen Action of New York re Progressive Leadership Awards event, October 5, 2005; letter from NYSUT president Richard Ianuzzi to local leaders re high budget defeat rate, professional development workshops available to build public relations skills, November 2
- Executive Committee 10/6/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  Agenda; outline of oral report of first vice president Maria Neira; resolution supporting creation of disaster relief and scholarship fund; BOCES Committee nominations; memo re management/confidential retiree health insurance, recommending shorter vesting period, October 3, 2005; report to the AFL-CIO Executive Council, "Overcoming Barriers to People of Color in Union Leadership," October 2005
- Executive Committee 9/16/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  President's Report; report of first vice president Maria Neira; report of second vice president Kathleen Donahue; report of secretary-treasurer Ivan Tiger; NYSUT membership comparison as of August 31, 2005; report of executive director Pauline Kinsella; 2006 Representative Assembly action items for Executive Committee and Board approval; membership maps; New York Teacher December 8, 2005, reprint re combating the achievement gap; description of "Academic Bill of Rights" and "Student Bill of Rights," created by California-based conservative think tank to counter liberal views in higher education
- Executive Committee 6/9/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  Agenda; minutes of May 24 meeting; report and outline of oral report of first vice president Maria Neira; requests for affiliation; NYSUT Building Corporation Board of Directors agenda; An Open Letter to [CUNY] Chancellor Goldstein on Academic Freedom, from Barbara Brown, president, Professional Staff Congress, June 3; document, "We Are CARU: the CUNY Alliance for Responsible Unionism," re "petition decrying the PSC's silence on the blacklisting of Israeli academics"
- Executive Committee 5/24/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  Agenda; report and outline of oral report of first vice president Maria Neira; report of executive director of Field & Legal Services Pauline Kinsella; NYSUT management list; list of officer liaisons to committees; 2005 delegate survey summary; 2005 Post RA Survey Summary; report on attendance at 2005 Representative Assembly press release and related materials re No Child Left Behind: Let's Get It Right campaign; memo re Forbes article and Attorney General probe into 403(b) tax-deferred annuities and the unions that endorse them, April 14
- Executive Committee 3/15/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  Agenda; report of first vice president Maria Neira; report of executive director of Field & Legal Services Pauline Kinsella; minutes of Executive Committee video conference of February 15; materials re Task Force on Value-Added Accountability/Assessment; handwritten notes
- Executive Committee 2/15/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  Agenda; report of first vice president; testimony of Alan Lubin, executive vice president, NYSUT, to the Senate Finance Committee and Assembly Ways and Means Committee, February 8 and 14; NYSUT press release, "Poll: Committee Chairs' Constituents Support Higher Taxes on Wealthy; Want Tax Revenue to Help Pay for Public Schools," February 14, 2005; survey results by Benchmark Polling Group; report by AFL- CIO Committee in the Evolution of Work, "The Changing Situation of Workers and Their Unions," February 1985, with cover note to AFT Executive Council, February 25, 2005
- Executive Committee 1/28/05, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 50)